<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes from diuers countries as, from [brace] Spaine, Antwerpe, Collin, Venice, Rome, the Turke, and the prince Doria : and how the arch-duke of Austria is intended to resigne his cardinall hat through his marrying with the king of Spaines daughter.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08137</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18504.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4029</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">34382802</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 34382802</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29088</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08137)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29088)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1901:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes from diuers countries as, from [brace] Spaine, Antwerpe, Collin, Venice, Rome, the Turke, and the prince Doria : and how the arch-duke of Austria is intended to resigne his cardinall hat through his marrying with the king of Spaines daughter.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 [i.e. 22] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Valentine Sims, and are to be sold in Gratious streete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1597.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Numerous errors in paging.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Library of Congress.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Europe --  History --  1492-1648.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29088:1"/>
            <p>NEWES from diuers countries. AS, From Spaine, Antwerpe, Collin, Venice, Rome, The Turke, and The prince Doria. And how the Arch-duke of Auſtria is intended to reſigne his Cardinall Hat; through his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying with the King of Spaines daughter.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>Seene and allowed.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at London by Valentine Sims, and are to be ſold in Gratious ſtreete. 1597.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:29088:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29088:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Newes from Antwerp, <date>the fifth day of Maie. 1597.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Cardinall Archduke which is yet at Bruxels, hath (as it is reported) aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled about 5000. men neere Calice and thoſe parts to ſpoile the country, and it is thought likewiſe that in the end of this moneth himſelfe will take the field with 6000. fighting men to attempt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what againſt the towne of Oſtend whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſtates haue ſent fiue other enſignes of footemen for the farther ſtrengthning of that garriſon.</p>
            <p>The ſtates had of late intended to ſurpriſe Graueling: but the practiſe being diſcouered, their men returned without perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming any thing.</p>
            <p>The Frenchmen encreaſing ſtill in power make towardes A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miens whereinto there is entred a certaine number of horſe and the ſaid Frenchmen inuading the country of Luxembrough, did on a ſodaine ſurprize the towne of Iunix, which after they had ſackt they ſet on fire, and thence marcht towards Lafertei, where not being able to effect their purpoſe, they roue vp and downe the prouince, doing euery where great hurte. For which cauſe the Cardinall hath ſent thither Colonel Berlotta with other Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines to withſtand the French, who ſeeke by ſuch attemptes to croſſe and hinder his proceedings.</p>
            <p>We are aduertiſed here by letters from Holland, of the arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall there of ſundry ſhips laden with diuers merchandizes, and ſtore of ready money, who report that the Engliſhmen hauing ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and ſakt the Port of Saint Martin, did afterward ſet it on fire with all the ſhippes within the harbour.</p>
            <p>On ſunday the bodies of Saint Flauia Domicila and of S. Hereo and Archileo Romanes, were remoued from the Church of S. Adrian to their owne Church, which is the title of Cardinal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ronio.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:29088:3"/>
            <p>On munday a counſell was called at Montecauallo, wherein the Archmadrite of Meſſina was beſtowed on a Sicilian. The Archbiſhop of Roan receiued his pall, and Cardinall Farneſe propounded a monaſterye in the Kingdome of Arragon in Spaine.</p>
            <p>On Tuſeday the Cardinall Marc Antonio Colona departed this life, leauing for heire of all goods, the Lord Martio Colona his nephue.</p>
            <p>On wendſday towards euening the Cardinall Ceſis &amp; Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignor Bonuiſi gaue commaundement to the Captaines which were appointed for Hungary, that on munday next they ſhoulde cauſe their ſouldiers to depart; whereupon certaine companies did yeſterday ſet forward, and the ſaid Bonniſi who doth like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to morrow take his iourney, hath already ſent his comiſſary to make prouiſion for the voyage.</p>
            <p>The Spaniſh Agentes heere are aduertiſed by letters from Praghe, that the Admirall of Arragon hath publiſhed in that court by order of the Catholike King, that the Lady Infant of Spaine was maried to the Cardinall Archduke, and that the Emperour will reſigne the kingdome of Bohemia vnto him, as alſo that he ſhalbe made king of Romanes, which is as much to ſay as heire and ſucceſſor in the Empire. Otherwiſe the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Maieſty will not giue him any ſtate leſt he ſhould diminiſh the Crowne of Spaine, vnleſſe perhaps he beſtow on him the Dutchy of Brittaine hauing recouered it from the French, as a thing belonging to the Lady Infants mother. That the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſhall reſigne the Archbiſhopricke of Toledo to Archduke Maximilian one of the brethren of the Prince of Spaines bride which ſhalbe. Who (as it is reported) muſt be conueied to her huſband in October next: vpon the publiſhing whereof the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors of Venice, the great Duke, and Savoy did in their princes names viſite and gratulate the catholike kings ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador.</p>
            <p>It is likewiſe reported, that the prince Doria his iorney into Spaine, is to fetch the Kings daughter, and conuey her into I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly, whence ſhe ſhalbe accompanied into Flanders by the count
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29088:3"/> of Fuentes, who hath order to conduct her to the cardinal Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke.</p>
            <p>The other night there were ſent from hence two Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into ſpaine, the one whereby the kings daughter may take to huſband the cardinall, the other that the prince may take to wife her that is betrothed vnto him, who ſhal this ſummer be conueied to Barcellona by the prince Doria in his gally royall with other gallies to the number of 30. whither the ſaid prince will come to receiue her.</p>
            <p>The great duke vnderſtanding that the catholike King wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted powder and other munition wherewith to furniſh his towns on the ſea coaſt of ſpaine and Portugall, eſpecially at this time, becauſe he feares they ſhalbe aſſaulted by the Engliſh fleete, his highneſſe did therefore cauſe a ſhip to be laden with 20000. bar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rels of powder and other munition, which he ſent into Spaine for a preſent to the catholike maieſtie: but the Florentines ſay that hee ſent the ſaide munition, to haue therefore ſo much corne graine. And the Ieſuites which are lately come, reporte for a certainetie, that the ſaide ſhip is long ſince arriued at Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cante.</p>
            <p>They write from Naples, that the viceroy hath built 4. new gallies, wherewith, togither with other ſhippes he purpoſeth to imbarke and carry into Spaine the third part of the footmen that were leuied in that kingdome, and there ſhould be leuied another third vnder the conduct of the marques of Treuiſo.</p>
            <p>They write from Florence, that the fort of Caſteldit ouer-a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Marſiglia, holdes for the great Dutcheſſe in the French kings name, becauſe the ſaid fort was taken by the ſouldiers of the other fortreſſe belowe which are kept there at the ſaide great ducheſſe coſt, by whoſe order the ambaſſadour of Tuſcane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring with him of France on tueſday, told him that whatſoeuer was done herein, was for the ſeruice of the moſt chriſtian maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and by the Duke of Guiſe his conſent, which, perceiuing that the captaine of the ſaid place had inteligence with the prince Doria ſent poſt for him to Marſiglia, that the ſouldiers might the more eaſily atchieue their enterpriſe.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:29088:4"/>
            <p>On thurſeday the ambaſſadors of Venice and of the great D. were together with the Catholike Kings Agent by the ſpace of foure houres in a chamber locked vnto them, but it is not known what or whereon they treated.</p>
            <p>Here are news of the archbiſhop of Siena his death, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed in his owne church, which place (it is thought) ſhall bee giuen to the cardinall Taruggi.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>Newes from Antwerp <date>the 14. of Maie. 1597.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>The Cardinall Archduke doth what hee can to put an armie into the field; but through want of mony his purpoſe goes ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forward: neither is it yet knowne what enterpriſe the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards will make, ſith the troups which were ſent forth, are retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto their garriſons, which moueth ſome to thinke that they will onely ſtrengthen and furniſh the frontier-townes.</p>
               <p>The forces which his highneſſe ſent to ſuccour Amiens, haue done nothing, becauſe they were not ſtrong enough to withſtand the French, who haue entrenched themſelues not farre from the army where they remain, keeping good watch, and the Spaniſh horſemen in Arras appoynted to ſuccour Amiens, can finde no meanes to enter the towne, ſith all the paſſages are ſtopt, and the ſouldiers within the towne repoſed ſmall confidence in the Burgeſſes, who begin to grow weary of perfourming the duetie of ſouldiers.</p>
               <p>The French men in the countrie of Luxembrough vnder the D. of Niuers do watch their opportunitie to worke, ſome ſpoile (and as the voice goeth) they will lay ſiege to Harlam, not farre from Baſtague, if they be not preuented by colonell Berlotta, whome his highneſſe hath ſent into thoſe partes,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From Rome <date>the 24. of the ſaid moneth.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>On wedneſday towardes night there came a poſt from the Prince Doria, and departed preſently to Naples to ſollicite the footmen, and brought word that the ſaid prince did on the twenty
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29088:4"/> day depart for Spaine, to fetch thence the kings daughter, and to conduct her into Italie: the which princeſſe (as it is reported) ſhall be entituled the Queene of Bohemia, for the Emperour and his brethren haue already graunted this title to the cardinal Archduke at the catholike Kings inſtance, by whoſe meanes the ſaide Cardinall ſhall bee made King of the Romanes, through helpe of his voyce as king of Bohemia: and ſhal furthermore be confirmed in the gouernement of Flaunders.</p>
               <p>They write from Naples that the gallies of Sicilie brought eight great canons from Palermo, which (as it is thought) ſhal be imployed in ſome attempt. That ſixe miles from the hauen a ſhip laden with corne belonging to the Centurion of Genoa, was caſt away, and therewith 100. marriners, 70. ſouldiers. That the 8000. footemen which were leuied in that kingdome, ſhall meete neare to the ſaid cittie to be imbarked in twenty gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies; and certaine ſhips and veſſels which were made ready: and that there was order giuen for the leuying of more men in the ſaide kingdome. They write from Sicilie, that there departed from Palermo foure ſhippes, laden with biſkets, and fiue more ready to depart laden likewiſe with biſkets.</p>
               <p>On wedneſday morning a counſell was called at Monteca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uallo wherein was propounded by the cardinall of Aquauma the church of Onarem vnder the principalitie of Berna, there was alſo propounded the biſhopricke of Cardoua in Spaine in the behalfe of the biſhop of Conia, and this muſt be propounded in the perſon of an other Spaniard.</p>
               <p>The knight Tomaſo Tomaſi, who was ſent ambaſſador in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Spaine by the duke of Parma, is gone (they ſay) to thanke his maieſtie, for hauing giuen him a wife, and in particular, one that is alied to the prince his ſonne.</p>
               <p>On ſaturday there came a poſt vnto the Pope, ſent to him from the cardinall Taruggi with newes, that hee had laboured and concluded a peace betweene the Dukes of Mantua and Parma: and therefore (ſay they) that theſe two princes wil per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally meete each other at Rlegio in Lombardy where the ſaid Cardinall, and the moſt excellent duke of Ferrara will bee
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29088:5"/> preſent: which newes hath cauſed maruellous great ioy in this court.</p>
               <p>On Sunday there was an abiuration of twelue men, whome they called heretikes, in S. Mineruaes church, where many car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalles were preſent: and it is reported, that of theſe twelue, three ſhall ſuffer death, of which one is a Florentine of the ſtocke of the Duzzi, who becauſe he is conſtant in his opinion, ſhall be burned aliue, the other two firſt putte to death, and then burnt, the reſt condemned, ſome to the gallies, ſome to priſon.</p>
               <p>By letters from Spaine bearing date the <hi>24.</hi> of April, and of the third of this preſent month, we are aduertized that the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the merchants was accorded on, becauſe the king will giue the ſaide merchants very good aſſignements after the rate of ten and an halfe <hi>pro cento</hi> for the olde parcell, and touching the new, he will pay them the one halfe preſently in ready mony, and for the reſt will giue very good aſſignes. It is alſo reported, that the Engliſhmen haue wonne the Iland of ſaint Martha neare the Tercere.</p>
               <p>It is ſaide, that the promotions of the Cardinall at the french Kings requeſts ſhal not be vntill September or Chriſtmas: and that cardinall Farneſe ſhal be ſent ambaſſador into Flanders to the cardinal Archduke.</p>
               <p>Monſignor Bonuiſi departed for Hungary on Wedneſday: ſo did alſo yeſterday all the companies that were in Rome, by order from the pope. The Celſo Celſi, and the captaine Biſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone du Teſe ſhal be made ſergeants of one third a peece, beſides the companies which they haue already. And of the horſe menne which ſhall be layed in theſe parts, ſeignior Flamino Delfino is appointed to haue charge.</p>
               <p>Newes likewiſe is brought that Monſignior Fabio Orſino is arriued at Praghe to treate with the Emperour of very great and weightie affaires which are not openly knowen.</p>
               <p>The cardinall Bandini is departed on his Legacie into Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mania: And the cardinalles of Prinli and Verona are gone for Loretto to imbarke themſelues in Ancona for Venice.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:29088:5"/>
               <p>It is reported that the Cardinall <hi>Dauilla</hi> is ſet in the Congregation of the Councell, and <hi>Gueuarra</hi> in that of the Biſhops.</p>
               <p>By reaſon of the Biſhop of <hi>Cattanaes</hi> death, that ſeate is voide, and reſts in the nomination of the Catholike king, yéelding <hi>25.</hi> thouſand crownes yéerely.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From Cullen <date>the 19. of the ſame moneth.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>WE are héere aduertiſed by letters from <hi>Bruxels,</hi> that the Cardinall Archduke hath renounced his hate in the Cathedrall Church, with the accuſtomed ceremonies, and that the Catholike King will both cauſe him to be made King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> by the Emperor and Princes Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and hath alſo aſſigned him a perpetuall reuenew of the Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Toledo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From Antwarpe, <date>the 21. of Maye 1597.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>THey ſay that the King of Fraunce, with the Duke of <hi>Maine</hi> is come to <hi>Corbi,</hi> hauing 60. peeces of Artillerie, and that his Maieſtie hath called backe the Horſemen which were about <hi>Amyens,</hi> for wante of Corne and other things, yet the footemen are very well intrenched, neither is there any preparation made héere as yet to ſuccour the ſaid Towne.</p>
               <p>They write from <hi>Amſterdam</hi> the 17. of this preſent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, that they haue newes, that parte of the ſaid Spaniſh fléete was arriued in Britaine: That <hi>Graue Maurice</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from the <hi>Haghe,</hi> with purpoſe to take the fielde, and that there are ſundrie Shippes laden with Corne come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Holland</hi> from diuers partes, whereby the price is falne
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29088:6"/> more then a thirde parte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From Coleine <date>the 26. of the ſame moneth.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>THe Spaniards are of late gone towards <hi>Berghe</hi> in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Veſſels built on the <hi>Rhein,</hi> carrying with them great prouiſion, and much ſtore of powder, but it is not knowne what they purpoſe to attempt. There are alſo other Spaniards in the fielde in Gielderland.</p>
               <p>They write out of Fraunce, that the King hauing mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterd and paide his Armie, made towards <hi>Amiens,</hi> his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces euery day encreaſing: and there was little hope that the Cardinall could ſuccour the ſaid towne, by reaſon of the great ſcarcitie of victuals through all Picardie.</p>
               <p>It was héere reported, that the States Souldiers had woone <hi>Venlo</hi> in Gelderland, but that at the laſt they were repulſed and beaten backe by the Towneſmen.</p>
               <p>It is ſaide for certaine, that the Popes holineſſe will by all meanes haue the rents of all the offices for two moneths for the warres of <hi>Hungary,</hi> for which cauſe alſo it is thought that the people ſhall be charged with a certaine ſumme of money.</p>
               <p>They write from <hi>Parma</hi> of <hi>Sinior marco Farneſe</hi> his ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall, who is looked for héere, being ſent by the Generall <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dobrandino,</hi> to informe the Pope what power the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour ſhall haue for his warre againſt the Turke: but ſome ſuppoſe that the ſaid Lordes returne is for certaine diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes.</p>
               <p>It is héere reported, that <hi>Don Iohn de Media</hi> is gone to <hi>Caſteldit</hi> with the great Dukes Galleis, and certaine ſhips laden with Munition, to aſſure altogether that Fortreſſe, by building a new Forte in the Iſland of <hi>Cachaſtraſſe,</hi> from whence they may batter <hi>Caſteldit.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:29088:6"/>
               <p>On Thurſday theſe companies of Souldiers did all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte on their iourney towardes <hi>Hungarie,</hi> marching with great ſpéede, ſo that there is hope that they wil ſhortly ariue in thoſe parts.</p>
               <p>They write from <hi>Bologna,</hi> that <hi>Sinior Marco Pio,</hi> and <hi>Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauio Anogodro,</hi> came néere to the walles of the ſaide Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and were diſcouered by the Courte as baniſhed men: they were purſued, but in vaine, for they ſaued themſelues within the territorie of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> onely a Gentleman of their company was taken and impriſoned.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sinior Ottauio Maſſimi,</hi> who was kept in priſon by the Duke of <hi>Segni</hi> vpon ſuſpition and iealouſie of his Wife, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet at libertie and on his iourney towardes <hi>Rome,</hi> had ſixe Harquebuzies diſcharged on him, about thrée miles on this ſide <hi>S Fiora,</hi> one of which ſtrooke him into the head, whereof he dyed preſently.</p>
               <p>Newes came on Monday that the Cardinall of Saint <hi>Clement,</hi> Legate in <hi>la Marca d'Ancona,</hi> hath taken either aliue or dead, all the <hi>Banditi</hi> which troubled that prouince.</p>
               <p>Signor <hi>Cümillo Capizucchi</hi> wil depart from hence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Hungarie,</hi> and the voice goeth that he ſhal be made Campe-maiſter in the Chriſtian Armie.</p>
               <p>Cardinall <hi>Taruggi</hi> arriued this euening, being returned from <hi>Lombardie,</hi> who hath eſtabliſhed a firme peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene the Dukes of <hi>Parma</hi> and <hi>Mantua,</hi> and hath for ſome reſpects ſuſpended as yet the enterview of the ſayde Princes, but they haue aſſigned their deputies, and there haue paſſed letters betwéene them for confirmation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And it is reported, that amongſt other things agréede on, this article is one: that all their former writings tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this matter ſhall be burnt.</p>
               <p>On Thurſday morning the aforeſaide perſons condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for religion, were firſt beheaded in the tower of <hi>Nona,</hi> and afterward burned in <hi>Campo de Fiore.</hi> The other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canted all that they written or ſpoken againſt the Pope.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:29088:7"/>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From Venice <date>the 23. of Maye.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>THey write from <hi>Genoa</hi> the tenth of this moneth, that two Galleys of Sauoye arriued there to ioyne with the other, for the conueying of the Prince <hi>Doria</hi> into Spaine, with <hi>Sinior Gambacortas</hi> footemen, which arriue dayly at the Forde: and the voice goeth, that the ſayde Prince will not depart vntill the comming of the <hi>Neapolitane</hi> footemen for whom he hath ſent.</p>
               <p>They write from <hi>Alba-Iulia</hi> the 14. of Aprill, that the two <hi>Ghrauſſi</hi> which were ſent from the great Turke, to the Prince, were diſpatched back againe by his Highneſſe, who ſent with them a Gentleman of his Court, on what affaires it is not knowne. That the Turkes haue built a Bridge on the Riuer of <hi>Danuby,</hi> wherevpon ſome great hurte is doubted. There was likewiſe reporte of a mightie Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh armie ſetting forwarde, whereof his Highneſſe did ſpeedily aduertiſe the Emperor, counſelling him to prepare for warre with all expedition.</p>
               <p>They write alſo from <hi>Vienna</hi> on the tenth of the ſame moneth, that there was made prouiſion for warre, but not ſo throughly as were requiſite. That they fortified certaine Baſtions there, the voyce ſtill holding, that the Gardens and houſes neere the walles ſhould be throwne downe, and the Trenches enlarged. That 170. footemen of <hi>Strigonia</hi> being all Wallons and Italians, put to flight 1500. Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Horſſemen in the Iſle of <hi>Strigonia,</hi> of which number none eſcaped, the moſt parte periſhed in the water, which ſéemeth miraculous. That the Boores were ſtill executed, and a hundreth more of them brought to <hi>Vienna,</hi> amongſt whom were ſome of the chiefe.</p>
               <p>They write from <hi>Craconia</hi> the third of this preſent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29088:7"/> that the Palatine of <hi>Chionia</hi> did ſtill perſiſt in his contumacie, leauing Souldiers, and preparing for warre of his owne authoritie: whereby the King ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to vſe force againſt him, which may bréede ſome greater matter, but there is hope that the Eſtates will be mediators betwéene them for the preuenting of farther troubles. And there is no farther talke of his Maieſties iourney into <hi>Suetia,</hi> ſince the Palatine of <hi>Vilnas</hi> anſwere at the Parliament, to his Commiſſioners.</p>
               <p>There are more certaine newes by letters from <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> that <hi>Cicala</hi> was not called backe vnto <hi>Porte.</hi> But contrariwiſe that the great Turke hath appointed him to tarrie ſtill at <hi>Argyrore,</hi> towardes which place a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine number of Souldiers was to be ſent to renew and ſtrengthen the garriſons of thoſe frontiers. The Perſian hauing in vaine demaunded reſtitution of certaine For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes, according to promiſſe made in the articles of the peace: and therefore the voyce held, that he purpoſed to take armes againſt the ſaid <hi>gran Sinior</hi> the great Turke, which entended not to make any reſtitution at all. And that <hi>Mahomet Baſſa</hi> was made Captaine generall of the armie in Hungarie.</p>
               <p>There are newes from <hi>Turin</hi> by Letters, of the firſt of this preſent moneth, that the Duke of <hi>Sauoye</hi> made pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration to paſſe the Mountaines, ſo ſoone as <hi>Mendoza</hi> Captaine of the Horſemen of <hi>Millaine</hi> ſhould ioyne with him, and hath in the meane time ſent a Garriſon to <hi>Suſa San Genis,</hi> (which is not taken by <hi>Digniere,</hi> as it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported) and to other places. All which, notwithſtanding ſome ſuppoſe that there is hope of prolonging the truce, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Dighera</hi> be in armes, and hath raiſed all <hi>Daulphine, Prouence, Auuerne,</hi> and other countries adiacent, hauing likewiſe attempted to raiſe the <hi>Switzers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are farther newes brought from <hi>Vienna,</hi> that the aforeſaid ouerthrow of the Turkes at <hi>Srigonia,</hi> hath much
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29088:8"/> encouraged the inhabitants both of the vpper and lower <hi>Hungarie,</hi> which offer themſelues with all readineſſe to performe their vttermoſt againſt the common enemie. It is yet farther reported, that the Emperour will marche foorth in perſon, if the Turke come to the ſiege of <hi>Vienna.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But others affirme, that there is a treatie of peace, and that the Prince of <hi>Tranſiluania</hi> will be a mediator betwéen them, which ſéemes to many a thing very vnlikely.</p>
               <p>For ſo much as is yet knowne, the controuerſies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Dukes of <hi>Parma</hi> and <hi>Mantua</hi> are very well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, and through the diligence of Cardinall <hi>Taruggi,</hi> and the great wiſdome of the moſt excellent Duke of <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rara.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They write from <hi>Praghe</hi> bearing date the tenth of this preſent moneth, that <hi>Sinior Gio: Franciſco Aldobrandino,</hi> did on the ſame day depart towardes <hi>Vienna</hi> with ſeauen Coaches, and that the Marquiſſe of <hi>Borgari</hi> muſt ſhortlye follow him. And they had intelligence that the Turke ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſent 6000. Ianiſaries to aſſure the paſſages through <hi>Tranſiluania, Moldania,</hi> and <hi>Valachia:</hi> the <hi>Tranſiluanians</hi> and <hi>Valachians</hi> ioyning their forces, had encountered and foilde the firſt Squadron, in ſuch ſorte that fewe eſcaped, and that they went forwarde to ſerue the other Squadrons in like manner. As alſo that the <hi>Bulgarians</hi> taking armes haue done ſome ſpoile vnto the Turkes.</p>
               <p>There are letters ſent from <hi>Rome,</hi> that the Cardinall Archduke hath renounced his Hatte vnto the Pope, and his Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Toledo</hi> to <hi>Don Sacio de Valori</hi> Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to the Prince of Spaine, reſeruing to himſelfe the pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a hundred thouſand Crownes, and that his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath in Dowrie the aſſignements of Portugall, which amounteth to foure hundreth thouſand Crownes
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29088:8"/> with the pretentions of the Infant (daughter to the King of Spaine) his Wife to the Dutchie of Britaine.</p>
               <p>We are aduertiſed from <hi>Auguſta,</hi> that there arriued at <hi>Olimo</hi> ſixe thouſand footemen, and two thouſand horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, all <hi>Vallons,</hi> which marche into <hi>Hungarie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is alſo reported that the moſt excellent <hi>Prouiditore Benbo</hi> hauing taken certaine of the <hi>vſcorchi</hi> and ſent them to <hi>Segna,</hi> they were preſently truſſed vs vp: which is an euident ſigne that the houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> is willing to make all the ſetiſfaction he may, to this moſt excellent ſtate.</p>
               <p>There came alſo the Lord <hi>Arrideo Borgonia</hi> Cup-bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to the Emperours Eaieſtie ſent aout the ſame matter, and being diſpatched here he muſt paffe preſently to Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine, to treat with that Duke, but vppon what affaires, it not as yet well knowne.</p>
               <p>They report from <hi>Millain</hi> that the Florentines haue driuen the Frenchmen from <hi>Cacaſtras</hi> or caſtledit.</p>
               <p>That the truce with <hi>Sauoy,</hi> was prolonged vntill the fiftéenth of this moneth, and that the ſaide Duke had ſent another Gentleman to the moſt Chriſtian King, it is not knowne wherefore.</p>
               <p>That the Knight <hi>Landriano</hi> was taken at <hi>Millan,</hi> and ſent to <hi>Malta,</hi> for what cauſe, it is not knowne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From Venice <date>the thirtith of May. 1597.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>THey write from <hi>Genoa</hi> the ſeuentéenth of this preſent moneth of the arriual there of Signor <hi>Franceſco de
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29088:9"/> Vera</hi> a Spaniard, and of the Senator <hi>Maionoldi</hi> of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane,</hi> which is now made Regent of that Citie in <hi>Spaine,</hi> in the place of <hi>Brugnolo,</hi> who is choſen Preſident of the Counſell of <hi>Millane,</hi> as alſo of the arriual of the Comen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dator <hi>Tomaſo Tomaſi</hi> the Duke of <hi>Parmas</hi> Ambaſſador, all which purpoſe to paſſe into <hi>Spain</hi> with the Prince <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia,</hi> who hath licence from the Senate, and is gone to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes <hi>poglio</hi> and <hi>Loano,</hi> whence on munday next hee will depart, there being already twelue Gallies ſent to the foorde to take in the footmen.</p>
               <p>There were newes from <hi>Cremoua,</hi> that they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by letters from <hi>Millane,</hi> where there arriued a poſte from <hi>Lyons,</hi> that the Spaniardes haue taken the towne of <hi>Maſiers</hi> in <hi>Champaigne.</hi> But ſmall credite is giuen to theſe newes, ſith the laſt letters from <hi>Millane</hi> doe menci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no ſuch matter.</p>
               <p>There came letters from <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> bearing date the ſeuenteenth of the laſt moneth, that <hi>Cicala</hi> hauing fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallie cleared himſelfe to the Sultane, ſhould returne to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and that it was likelie he ſhould bee made chiefe Viſir, it being alſo thought that hee ſhoulde bee ſent Generall into <hi>Hungarie,</hi> and that then the grand Signor would not goe himſelfe.</p>
               <p>That there is a woonderfull ſcarcitie, eſpeciallie of beaſtes.</p>
               <p>That there are ſundrie ſpéeches and opinions touching the Armie, ſome ſuppoſing that onlie ſome fewe Gallies ſhall be ſent foorth: But if certaine articles betweene the grande Signor and the King of <hi>France</hi> were agreed on, that then his Highneſſe would ſend 70. or 80. Gallies to his ayde.</p>
               <p>That the report of the Catholique Kinges procéedinges
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29088:9"/> in preiudice of the French kings Maieſtie, was much diſpleaſant, and that the great Turke was deſirous that the moſt Chriſtian King ſhould accept the capitulations offered, that he might afterward ſend foorth a Fleet of 150 Sayles to hurt &amp; ſpoyle the Catholique King by al meanes poſſible. That vpon <hi>Cycalas</hi> comming the great Turke would go to <hi>Adrinopoli</hi> to encourage his people, being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to drawe them foorth by wonderful threates, they were ſo diſmayed, fearing ſome greater loſſe then they had ſuſtained the yeare before. And that to make them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that he means to take the field, the Standerd which is woont to be borne before him was again diſplayd. That the <hi>Mulſti</hi> and other <hi>Papaſsi</hi> conſulting togither, had plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie tolde the grand Signor, that he ſhoulde not ſuffer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be ruled by the Sultan which were herewith much offended.</p>
               <p>It is ſignified by letters from <hi>Vienna,</hi> bearing date the 17. of this preſent moneth, that the Baſſa of <hi>Boſsina</hi> with a good number of Souldiours will lay ſiege to <hi>Caniſa,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting the grande Signors power: and the imperial Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines haue now thought on ſundrie meanes for the reſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that place. That the Turkes of <hi>Papa. Veſprino. Palotta. S. Martin</hi> and other places aſſemble themſelues at <hi>Iaurino,</hi> ſcouring the plaines and making no account of our Forces, that on the day aboue written the Generall <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dobrandino</hi> came to <hi>Vienna</hi> and was met by Archduke <hi>Mathias:</hi> that the Marquiſſe of <hi>Borgari</hi> and Signor <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranti di Roſsi</hi> wil ſhortlie likewiſe be there: that the Prince of <hi>Tranſylvanias</hi> wife was looked for, as alſo the Prince of <hi>Anholt</hi> which (they ſay) ſhall be made Archduke <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milians</hi> Lieutenant. That the <hi>Tranſylvanian</hi> hath ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrwn ſixteen thouſand Turks and Tartars of <hi>Valachia</hi> and <hi>Moldavia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They write from <hi>Turin</hi> of <hi>Mendozzas</hi> arriuall which offered great ayde to the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> if the Frenchmen
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29088:10"/> ſhould ſtirre. That it was againe reported how the ſaide Gouernour of <hi>Me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>z</hi> had intelligence with the Cardinall Archduk, the ſaid Gouernor being ſomewhat ſuſpected by the King. And it was thought that the ſaid Cardinall had reſolued on that enterpriſe, making ſhew outwardlie as if he purpoſed to aſſault ſome other place. That his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Savoy</hi> hath ſent away <hi>Martinengo</hi> with other Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and all the footmen, towardes <hi>Ciamberi,</hi> where the whole Armie ſhould aſſemble, it being held for certain that the warre ſhal continue, howſoeuer the truce be prolonged</p>
               <p>They write from <hi>Lyons</hi> the 14. of this preſent moneth that <hi>Diguiere</hi> and the Gouernor of <hi>la Franche Contee</hi> did meete together and after conference determined that the ſaid <hi>Diguiere</hi> ſhould make roads into <hi>Savoy</hi> and <hi>Piemont,</hi> the Baron of <hi>Luz</hi> into <hi>la Franch Contee</hi> and that <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur du Perault</hi> ſhould ſcowre the countrey aboue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tezelo.</hi> Although that the forces of <hi>Sauoy</hi> together, with the aide ſent from <hi>Millan,</hi> did exceed their number. They write from <hi>Paris,</hi> that the King was ſtill at <hi>S. Germans,</hi> purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing immediatlie after he had cleared himſelfe, to goe vnto the Camps in <hi>Picardie,</hi> which conſiſteth of a thouſand foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and 1500. horſe beſides as manie more which are to come with the King.</p>
               <p>They write from <hi>Marſiglia</hi> that thoſe inhabitants were all mooued with the newes of <hi>Cachaſtraſſe,</hi> and did there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore builde a fort ouer againſt it to beat and reduce it again to their ſubiection.</p>
               <p>We are aduertiſed by letters from the ſea that the <hi>Clar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſsimo Paſqualigo,</hi> Captaine of the Gulfe hath taken thrée Turkiſh Foyſts and two Brigandines being part of thoſe that ſpoild the ſhip <hi>Sylueſtra.</hi> The Turkes were all put to the ſword: and it is reported that they found aboue ſeuen thouſand Crownes in ready coyne and much of that mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize which was aboord the ſaide Ship, which together with the money ſhal remain to the ſaid Signor <hi>Paſqualigo</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:29088:10"/> and two Captaines of two other Gallies, which at that time were with him.</p>
               <p>They write from <hi>Alba Iulia,</hi> that the Turkiſh power doth dayly increaſe towards <hi>Danuby,</hi> that they are now allready fiftie thouſand ſtrong, and haue built a Bridge, for which cauſe the <hi>Tranſiluanian</hi> made all prouiſion neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, doubting greate inconuenience, if the Turkes ſhould bend their force againſt him, and his ſuccours be ſlowe in comming.</p>
               <p>They write from <hi>Milane</hi> the 28. of this preſent moneth, that they haue intelligence from Spaine, how the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick King is in perfect health and gone to <hi>Eſcuriall.</hi> That the Earle of <hi>Fuentes</hi> dooth with all dilligence prepare for warre. That the King of <hi>Fez</hi> is in armes againſt the Spaniard, and hath layde ſiege to <hi>Centa.</hi> That the Duke of Sauoy made prouiſion to withſtande <hi>Dighera,</hi> who was counſelled by <hi>Monſieur Iacob</hi> late being returned from <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> that he ſhould prouide for warre, becauſe the Souldiers of <hi>Don Alfonſo de Aualos</hi> were not yet gone, but would tarrie certaine dayes at the ſaid Dukes requeſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From Venice <date>the 6. of Iune, 1597.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>WE were aduertiſed by the laſt moneths letters from <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> of the Gréeke Patriarchs death, in whoſe place he of <hi>Alexandria</hi> a Grecian alſo ſhall ſuccéed, with condition that he labour for a peace with the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, the <hi>Tranſiluanian</hi> and <hi>Michael</hi> the <hi>Voiuoide</hi> of <hi>Vallachia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They write from <hi>Genou</hi> the 24. of the laſt moneth, how the Galley Royall with others, wente towardes <hi>Poggio,</hi> there to take in the Prince <hi>Doria,</hi> who was on the fiftéenth day to depart for Spaine.</p>
               <p>There came letters from <hi>Vienna,</hi> bearing date likewiſe the 24. day, how the Chriſtians going by night to <hi>Totta</hi> threw down 1 of the gates, and ſo taking it, ſlew all the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29088:11"/> Turkes within. Wherevpon new prouiſion was made of men and munition for the kéeping of that place, being a verie fitte paſſage from <hi>Buda</hi> to <hi>Alba egale.</hi> They ſignifie alſo how the <hi>Siculy</hi> offered the Prince of <hi>Tranſilua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> that if he would graunt them their their auncient Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, that then they would aide him with fiftéene thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men, alledging that the cauſe of their returne to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of that houſe, whereof the ſaid Princes Wife doth linneally deſcend, is to eſchewe the daungers which are likely to enſue of the wars.</p>
               <p>They write from <hi>Tautinio,</hi> that <hi>Dighera,</hi> beſides his greate preparations for warre, hath leuied a new ſixe thouſand men more in <hi>Doulphine,</hi> and in <hi>Burgoine</hi> a farre greater number. For which cauſe (as they ſignifie from <hi>Millain</hi>) the duke of <hi>Sauoy</hi> hath moſt earneſtly intreated the Cunſtable that he ſhould not ſend away the troupes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Flaunders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is farther reported that they of <hi>Ciambrie</hi> did mutiue and refuſed to haue Souldiers in their houſes.</p>
               <p>They write from <hi>Marſiglia,</hi> that the Duke of Guiſe was at high wordes with certaine Lordes of <hi>Prouence:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon the Parliament of <hi>Aix,</hi> vndertooke to pacifie and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grée them.</p>
               <p>They write from <hi>Cracouia,</hi> that there are great forces ſent dayly to the frontiers of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and fifteene thouſand horſemen in a readynes to march into <hi>Toldania,</hi> vppon ſome new ſuſpicions of the <hi>Tranſiluanian</hi> betwene whom and the two breethren <hi>Battori:</hi> there are ſome controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies newly ſprong: But <hi>Malaſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>na</hi> the Popes <hi>Nuncio</hi> ſought by all meanes to accorde them. The <hi>Ruſſian</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror is yet aliue, contrary to the former reporte, but true it is, that he was euen at the point of death. There was ſpéech that another Ambaſſador ſhould be ſent vnto him with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents and offer of ayde againſt the Turke, who hath of late greatly moleſted him by ſtirring vp againſt him a faction
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29088:11"/> in the fauour of one who intends to ſuccéede in that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome after the ſaide Emperors diſceaſſe.</p>
               <p>There came letters from <hi>Paris,</hi> bearing date the twelfe of the laſt moneth, which ſignifieth that the King did on the ſame day depart towarde <hi>Picardie,</hi> Monſieur <hi>Tremouille</hi> being in the field with 1500. Horſe, and 2000. footemen le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uied out of <hi>Poictou.</hi> That there doe daily reſort vnto his Maieſtie great forces from all parts of the kingdom, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is thought the number of his armie will amount to thirty thouſand fighting men all French, beſides the Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers, Engliſh, Scottiſh, and Dutch, which he will haue in pay: ſo that the warre will now be greater then euer it was. <hi>Corſo</hi> is gone into <hi>Languedock</hi> to aſſault the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards from the ſide of <hi>Perpignan.</hi> The Marqueſſe <hi>du Pont</hi> is at the Courte about his mariage with the Kings ſiſter, which together with a hundreth other chiefe perſonages ſhould become Catholick.</p>
               <p>The newes from <hi>Sicill</hi> is, that in ſome ports of that I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land certaine <hi>Venecian</hi> ſhips were ſtayde to be ſent into Spaine with men, Biſcots and other prouiſions, out of which ſaid ſhippes the great part of the Marriners fled, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would not be employed in that voyage.</p>
               <p>There are farther newes from <hi>Vienna,</hi> that the ſurpriſe of <hi>Tatta</hi> was atchieued by <hi>Signior Polfi,</hi> who hauing left there a thouſand Souldiers for defence of the ſaid place, went to ioyne himſelfe with <hi>Nadaſdi</hi> and other principall Captaines, whoſe number will be in all eyght thouſand footemen, and two thouſand horſe, all olde Souldiers, with which power and other forces that daily reſorte vnto them, the ſaide Captaines purpoſe to vndertake ſome other en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe, before the enemy ſhall haue aſſembled his whole armie, which he cannot doo before the 24. of Iuly. That there were ſent many ſpies from <hi>Vienna</hi> to certaine Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages, and about a hundreth more of the chiefeſt of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Bores were put to death.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:29088:12"/>
               <p>Beſides the two hundreth footemen which were brought hither the other day by <hi>Todino,</hi> there are come two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth more, leuyed by <hi>Conte Vgocione Rangone,</hi> who are on the Sea ſide, and muſt be ſent to the Generall <hi>Bembo</hi> into <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> vnleſſe this moſt excellent Senate ſhall otherwiſe determine.</p>
               <p>They write from Flaunders, that thoſe of <hi>Amiens</hi> haue put foorth of the Towne to the number of eyght hundreth women and children, by reaſon of ſome wante of victuals, and that they might the better holde out.</p>
               <p>They reporte yet farther from <hi>Vienna,</hi> that the Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of <hi>Comar</hi> and <hi>Viuar</hi> ioyning themſelues, made a rode within eyght myles of <hi>Buda,</hi> and woone a place called <hi>Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uar,</hi> killing many Turkes, and taking twentie priſoners, which place hauing ſacked they ſet on fire.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Sinior Polfis</hi> Lieutenant in <hi>Strigonia</hi> had ſent vnto him a Turke who was taken with letters about him. That at the winning of <hi>Tatta</hi> they tooke the <hi>Begh</hi> and other principall Turkes. That they haue intelligence from <hi>Tranſyluania,</hi> how that people hath graunted to the Prince foure Florence of euery houſe.</p>
               <p>They write from <hi>Milane</hi> that <hi>Don Alfonſo de Aualos</hi> his troopes began to marche through Flaunders towardes Sauoye, and that the Duke thereof would haue no longer truce with Fraunce vnleſſe it were for two or thrée yéeres, but eyther abſolute peace or warre, becauſe theſe ſhort pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longings did put his Highneſſe to as great charges, as he ſhould be at an action of warre: wherefore he made great preparation, as did alſo <hi>Dighera</hi> on the other ſide.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:29088:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
